Guide to Otto Ege's Original Leaves from Famous Bibles M4005
Special Collections and University Archives, Colgate University Libraries
- A leaf from a Germantown Bible, Germantown: Gedrukt bey Christoph Sauer, 1763 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  The second edition of the first Bible issued in a literary tongue in North America, printed by Christopher Sauer, the younger. Luther's version was adopted for the text. The third issue of 3000 (1776) was still unbound when the Battle of Germantown was fought (1777), and nearly the entire edition of this Dunkard publisher was used by the British soldiers for gun wadding. A paper mill, a type foundry, and a bindery were established by the versatile Sauer for his work. Sauer wrote: "the price of our nearly finished Bible in plain binding with a clasp will be eighteen shillings, but to the poor and needy we have no price."
- A leaf from the Baskerville Cambridge Bible, Printed by John Baskerville, Printer to the University, 1763 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  The magnum opus of Baskerville, England's greatest type-founder and printer. For the printing of this imperial folio Bible, he moved his press from Birmingham to Cambridge. As he was able to secure only 264 subscribers (at four guineas each) for the edition of 1250 copies, he had to borrow 2000 pounds to complete the work. It is a paradox that Baskerville should have issued, at great financial loss, several editions of the Bible when he "unblushingly avowed not only his disbelief of, but his contempt for revealed religion, and that in terms too gross for repetition." His Cambridge Bible is one of the four monumental printed editions- the other three being the Gutenberg 42 Line Bible, the Doves Press Bible, and the Rogers Oxford Lectern Bible.
- A leaf from the "Quakers' Bible", London: W. Richardson and S. Clark, 1764 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  This original version, on which Anthony Purver, a member of the Society of Friends, is said to have spent thirty years, was never recognized by the Society, and was never reprinted. Purver invested and lost practically all his money in the venture. (Darlow and Moule 862)
- A leaf from a Baskerville Birmingham Bible, Birmingham: Printed by John Baskerville, 1769 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Baskerville, England's greatest type-founder and printer, had announced his retirement from active printing the year before. He returned to the press, however, and hastily printed this folio Bible to compete with a crudely printed one issued by his most vituperative enemy, Nicholas Boden, and his former senior workman, Robert Martin. This Bible, although far inferior to his Cambridge Bible, was a financial success.
- A leaf from the Bible of The Revolution, Philadelphia. Printed by R. Aitken, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  The first Bible in English to be printed in America was issued to fill a need created by war, since no Bibles were being imported. In 1781 Aitkens petitioned Congress for endorsement and financial aid to issue this Bible. On September 10, 1782, a resolution was passed-"The United States in Congress assembled highly approve the pious and laudable undertaking of Mr. Aitkens....they recommend this edition of the Bible to the inhabitants of the United States...." George Washington wrote a friend,"It would have pleased me well, if Congress had been pleased to make such an important present (a copy of this Bible) to the brave fellows, who have done so much for the security of their Country's rights and establishment. Only 32 complete copies are known to be extant.
- A leaf from the First Delaware New Testament, Wilmington: Printed and Sold by Peter Brynberg and Samuel Adams, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  This exceedingly rare testament appears to have escaped all bibliographers, including such authorities as J. Wright (Early Bibles of America); E.B. O'Callaghan (A List of Editions of the Holy Scriptures and Parts thereof, Printed America previous to 1860); and P. Marion Simms (The Bible in America). The next issue in Delaware appeared in 1802, under the imprint of Peter Brynberg alone. On account of the poor quality of paper used in Colonial Bibles and the hard service they received, examples are in many instances scarcer than in the case of the monumental Gutenberg Bible, issued nearly four hundred year earlier.
- A leaf from a First Thomas Quarto Bible, Worcester: Isaiah Thomas, 1791 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  The first quarto Bible in English published in America. Printed by Isaiah Thomas, whom Franklin called the "Baskerville of America". Its price was seven dollars, and to make payment easy, there was a provision that "the Publisher will receive one half the sum...in the following articles, viz. Wheat, Rye, Indian Corn, Butter, or Pork, if delivered at his store in Worcester, or at the store of himself and Company in Boston, by the 20th day of December, 1790." Thomas used thirty different editions of the King James Bible in preparing this text, and had every sheet examined by the clergymen of Worcester.
- A leaf from the Thomas Greek New Testament, Excudebat Isaias Thomas. Jun: Wigorniae, Massachusettensi, 1800 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  The earliest Greek Testament printed in America. The Worchester Press also produced some of the early American editions of the English Bible. Franklin called it the "Baskerville (Press) of America." This Testament was reprinted by the same printer in Boston (1814). (Darlow and Moule 4775)
- A leaf from a Thomson's Bible, Philadelphia: Printed by Jane Aitken, No. 71 North Third Street, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  The first translation of the Septuagint into English by Charles Thomson, who was the first Secretary of Congress, and who retired from that position to continue his Biblical studies (1789). The importance of this version, the result of twenty years' labor with little or no assistance of reference material or scholars, has frequently been recognized. It was freely consulted by the revision committee of 1881. (Darlow and Moule 1006)
- A leaf from The Immaculate Bible, Sir D. Hunter Blair and J. Bruce, Edinburgh, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  A special issue of the Bible, consisting of twenty-five copies only. Dibdin's Library Companion calls this a "a more beautiful book than the vaunted diamond-letter Bible of Richelieu." (Darlow and Moule 1019)
- A leaf from the Pickering "Diamond" Greek Testament, Londini: Gulielmus Pickering, 1828 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  The smallest Greek Testament ever published. The sizes of type employed is known as ""diamond", and there are sixteen lines to an inch. William Pickering was England's most important bookseller and publisher at this time. His series of miniature books, now known as Diamond Classics, were then regarded, and still are, as a great achievement in typesetting and printing. (Darlow and Moule 4816)
- A leaf from the Revised Version New Testament, New York: R. Worthington, 770 Broadway, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  In 1870 the convocation of Canterbury appointed a committee to revise the King James Version. Scholars of many denominations from England and America shared in this undertaking. Strict rules eliminated radicalism; yet 36,191 changes were made in the New Testament alone. The reception of this work was unprecedented. It was released in May, and before the end of the year over 2,000,000 copies were sold in London, and nearly 400,000 in New York. Several newspapers even went so far as to print the entire text. (May 22)
- A leaf from the Polychrome Bible, New York. Dodd, Mead, and Company, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  A new translation from the Hebrew into English under the direction of the great Shakespearean scholar, Horace Howard Furness. Original sources used by the translator are indicated by the background of different colors. Eight tints or colors were used in Joshua alone: dark red, light red, dark blue, light blue, purple, green, brown, and orange. The cost of editing and color printing was so great, that only a few books of the Bible were issued and the undertaking was then discontinued.
- A leaf from the Doves Bible, The Doves Press No. 1 The Terrace Hammersmith, 1903-1905 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  The King James Version, edited by Rev. F. H. Scrivener for the syndics of the University Press, Cambridge, England, and printed by Emery Walker and T.J Cobden Sanderson. The work is printed in "Doves" type, a "translation" of the famous fifteenth century font of Jenson by Walker. The Doves type is frequently referred to as the finest formal book type of all time. The text was set by one compositor and printed on a one-hand press. This monumental Bible is, nevertheless, one of the greatest typographical masterpieces produced.
- A leaf from a Miniature Bible, Edinburgh: Nimmo, Hay and Mitchell, Ltd., 1919 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  A miniature facsimile of the Robert Burns family Bible. The printing of small Bibles, generally known as "Bijou," "Diamond," or "Thumb" Bible interested many printers from the early seventeenth century to the present day. Photo-engraving now makes any scale possible, but there still remain technical difficulties in inking, printing, and binding these miniature Bibles.
- A leaf from the Nonsuch Bible, London. The Nonesuch Press, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  King James Version. Typography by Francis Meynell; printing by the Oxford University Press. The publications of the Nonesuch Press are noted for presenting significant texts in a beautiful format, for book collectors who "also use books for reading."
- A leaf from the Rogers Oxford Lectern Bible, Oxford. Printed at the University Press, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  King James Version printed in a special cutting of "Centaur" type by Bruce Rogers, who also established the format, typographical layout, and for six years supervised the printing at the University Press. A unique copy of this Bible, printed on special paper was presented by Mr. Rogers to Library of Congress. The edition was limited to two hundred copies. It is a Bible in the "Great Tradition," and equals, if it does not excel, any other Bible produced since the invention of printing, in beauty, dignity, and legibility. This is the supreme achievement of the greatest contemporary typographer.
- A leaf from Bible, Written in minuscule hand, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Creation Commentary
- A page from printed Book of Hours, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Illuminated Manuscript, Boucicant Groupp, Psalm 31 "Beat", Paris. MS 9
- A page from a Scriptorum, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Private Purchase. MS 2
- Unidentified leaf, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Unidentified leaf, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Unidentified leaf, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)